Finding Aid for Sanford Rossen papers and photographs 1960-1984
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Sanford Rossen Papers and Photographs 1960-1984, 1970-1983
Rossen, Sanford, 1927-1984.
3.75 linear feet
973 Aa 2
Michigan architect, mainly with firms Sanford Rossen A.I.A. Architects and Rossen-Neumann Associate in Southfield, Michigan, best known for design of several outdoor music venues, collection is primarily of buildings designed by Rossen with some papers related to various projects.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Geraldine Elias in June and August of 1996. Donor no. 8486.
The collection is open for research.
Michigan architect Sanford Rossen was born in Detroit in 1927 and died in 1984 at age 56. A graduate of Central High School, he served in the United States Navy before attending the University of Michigan's school of architecture. While earning a Bachelor of Architecture at Michigan, he was elected to membership in Tau Sigma Delta Architectural Honorary and received the American Institute of Architects' School Gold Medal, the highest award the architectural school bestows upon a student.
Upon graduation in 1951, Rossen worked for a number of Michigan architects as a project designer and project manager. In 1957, he founded Sanford Rossen A.I.A. Architects in Southfield, Michigan. Commissions included a variety of building types -- office structures, hotels, industrial buildings, banks, medical facilities, single and multi-family housing, theaters, race tracks, and commercial and office interiors. In 1964, the firm won a national design competition for the Elmwood Park Urban Redevelopment project in Detroit.
From 1968 to 1981, Rossen was in partnership with a former employee, Kenneth Neumann. Rossen-Neumann Associates consistently won awards for major projects, among them a national design competition for the Villa Site urban renewal area in Evansville, Indiana. The firm received widespread recognition for its design of outdoor music pavilions, most significantly Pine Knob in Michigan and Poplar Creek in the Chicago area. Other award winning projects included American Office Park (Southfield), Young Israel Synagogue (Southfield), Cleaners Hanger Company (Bloomfield), Troy Place Office Complex, and Farmington Professional Pavilion. When the partnership terminated in 1981, Rossen formed Sanford Rossen & Associates in the same year.
Rossen served for nine years on the Southfield, Michigan Planning Commission and was active in committee work for the Detroit chapter of the American Institute of Architects. He maintained contact with the University of Michigan, and was an adjunct professor in the College of Architecture and Urban Planning. He also lectured at Lawrence Institute of Technology School of Architecture in Southfield. A newspaper article at the time of Rossen's death, while recounting numerous exemplary achievements in commercial and public structures, reported that his favorite buildings were three houses, including the one he and his family lived in for twenty-five years on a wooded tract on Mulberry Court in Southfield, Michigan.
The collection is organized into four series: Miscellaneous Papers (.25 linear ft.); Photographs: Prints (1 linear ft.); Photographs: Slides (.5 linear ft.); and Photographs: Oversized and Mounted Prints (2 linear ft.)
The Sanford Rossen Collection is comprised almost entirely of black and white photographs and color slides of buildings and complexes designed by Sanford-Neumann & Associates during the 1970s. There are a few folders of projects undertaken in the 1960s and in the early 1980s, but the bulk of the material represents the period during which Rossen was associated with Kenneth Neumann. Although the collection includes some slides and photographs of architectural drawings, there is little of substance in this regard, and there is virtually no printed documentation related to individual buildings. The collection will therefore best serve the researcher interested in the visual representation of newly constructed buildings in this time period.
Rossen utilized the services of Balthazar Korab, an internationally acclaimed Detroit-based photographer, to capture on film the essence of many of his buildings. (In 1964, Korab was awarded the American Institute of Architects' Medal for Photography of Architecture, and his photographs have been exhibited in numerous major galleries, including the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Detroit Institute of Arts.) Rossen had numbers of these prints dry-mounted to hang on office walls and featured others in marketing materials. Some of the photographs are signed by Korab, but the majority are not, and for most, the identity of the photographer is unknown. Researchers wishing to study examples of effective and exceptional architectural photography, however, will find the collection a rich resource, particularly for Michigan area buildings.
Subjects:
Rossen, Sanford, 1927-1984.; Sanford Rossen & Associates.; Rossen/Neumann Associates.; Architects--Michigan.; Architecture--Michigan--Oakland County.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Business parks--Michigan.
Contributors:
Korab, Balthazar.
Genre/Form:
Architectural photographs.; Photographs.
- Miscellaneous Papers
  The series Miscellaneous Papers is slight, yet important because it is the only source of information in the collection beyond the visual. Most significant and useful is the marketing catalog Sanford Rossen & Associates Architects / Planners. Approximately forty projects are highlighted in its high quality black and white pages; browsing the catalog is the most efficient way to become familiar with Rossen's work in the 1970s. The folder entitled "Legal and Financial Papers" consists mainly of a few documents related to the dissolution of the Rossen-Neumann partnership. The series contains a folder of publications, each focusing on a building for which the firm was awarded an honor or one in which the firm was featured. Titles include American Institute of Steel Construction, Building Progress, Masonry, Creative Ideas in Glass and Michigan Society of Architects. Researchers wishing to attach a date to a project will find the "Job List, 1957-1983" helpful.
  - Articles and Awards (Box 1)
  - Job List 1957-1983 (Box 1)
  - Legal and Financial Papers 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Marketing Brochure: Sanford Rossen & Associates: Architects / Planners (Box 1)
  - Proposal: American Redevelopment Program: Elmwood Park 1964 (Box 1)
  - Publications Re: Projects 1970s (Box 1)
    (2 folders)
- Photographs: Prints
  The bulk of the collection is the Photographs: Prints series. Folders are arranged alphabetically by project. In addition to the folders in this series, there are two boxes of larger prints in the series Photographs: Oversized and Mounted Prints. A "see also" note directs the user to the appropriate oversized box. A majority of the prints are black and white images; however there are a few color prints scattered throughout the series.
  - 26600 Telegraph Rd.: Southfield, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Alpha Industries Office and Plant: Novi, Michigan (Box 1)
  - American Federal Savings and Employees Insurance of Wausau: Southfield, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Beckwith Evans General Offices: Troy, Michigan (Box 1)
    (see also 3 mounted prints Box 3)
  - Birmingham Arcade: Birmingham, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Bloomfield Professional Pavilion: Bloomfield, Michigan (Box 1)
    (see also 4 mounted prints Box 3)
  - Bookpeople: Birmingham, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Burton Abstract and Title Company: Headquarters: Troy, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Cadillac House Hotel: Detroit, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Chrysler Realty Office Building Complex: Northfield, Troy, Michigan (Box 1)
  - City National Bank Branch and Office Building: Bloomfield Township, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Cleaners Hangar Company: Bloomfield, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Crowley Milner & Company: Troy, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Daily, R.E. & Company: Southfield, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Detroit Automobile Dealers Association: Troy, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Elmwood Park Project, American Redevelopment Corporation (Box 1)
  - Fairlane Office and Research Building: Dearborn, Michigan (Box 1)
    (see also 1 mounted print Box 3)
  - Farmers and Merchants State Bank: Sebewaing, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Farmington Professional Pavilion: Farmington, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Flint State Office Building: Flint, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Florists Trans World Delivery National Headquarters / Trio Restaurant: Southfield, Michigan (Box 1)
    (see also 1 mounted print in Box 3)
  - Foamade Industries: Pontiac Township, Michigan (Box 1)
    (see also 2 mounted prints Box 3)
  - Franklin Wright Settlements Camp: Orion Township, Michigan (Box 1)
  - H & S Evansville (Box 1)
  - Jaffe, Snider, Raitt, Garratt & Heuer Law Offices: Detroit, Michigan (Box 1)
  - J.K. Lasser Company Interiors: Southfield, Michigan (Box 1)
  - K Mart Bee Ridge Square Office Building (Box 1)
  - Kimberly Scott Building: Troy, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Korman Office Building (proposed) (Box 1)
  - Kyoto Fairlane Restaurant: Dearborn, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Lahser & Northwestern Project; Farmington Hills, Michigan? (Box 1)
  - Liberty State Bank: Troy, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Lincoln Park Senior Citizens Residence: Lincoln Park, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Macomb Professional Building: Warren, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Manufacturers Bank of Southfield: Southfield, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Massachusetts Mutual (Box 1)
    (see also mounted print in Box 3)
  - Meteor Photo Company: Troy, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Metropolitan Federal Savings Headquarters: Shelby Township, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Metropolitan Savings Branch: Farmington Hills, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Michigan Life National Casualty Building: Southfield, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Michigan State Fair Master Plan: Detroit, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, 5 prints (Box 1)
    (see also 9 mounted prints in Box 4)
  - Portraits and Office (Box 1)
  - Pre-1960 Project Photographs (Box 1)
  - Negatives (Box 1)
  - Nemo's West Restaurant: Dearborn, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Omni Twin Office Building (Box 1)
  - Pavilions / Music Theatre (Pine Knob; Poplar Creek): Independence Township, Michigan,; Irving, Texas; Hoffman Estates, Illinois (Box 1)
    (see also 5 mounted prints Box 4)
  - One Port Huron Inn: Port Huron, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Residences (Box 1)
    (see also 4 mounted prints Box 4)
  - General (Box 1)
  - Summer Home Complex: Lexington, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Rosin and Rosin Office (Box 1)
    (see also 1 mounted print Box 4)
  - Ross Brody Office Building (Box 1)
  - Salvation Army Echo Grove Camp: Leonard, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Service Bureau Corporation (Box 1)
  - Singer Office Plaza: Southfield, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Sperry & Hutchinson: Southfield, Michigan (Box 1)
  - St. Joseph Mercy Hospital Medical Office: Ann Arbor, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Starkel Office Building: Troy, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Terry Barr Sales Office Building: Southfield, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Trenton Clinic (Box 1)
  - Troy Place Office Complex: Troy, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Twin Office Building Project: Schaumburg, Illinois (Box 2)
  - United Midwest Bancorporation Ltd: Troy, Michigan (Box 2)
    (see also 2 mounted prints in Box 4)
  - Village Green of Farmington: Farmington, Michigan (Box 2)
  - Weight Watchers of Eastern Michigan: Southfield, Michigan (Box 2)
  - Weissman Clinic Medical Office (Box 2)
  - Whitehouse and Hardy (Box 2)
  - Wineman Project (Box 2)
  - Woodcreek Pavilion Office Development: Farmington Hills, Michigan (Box 2)
  - Woodfield Office Center: Schaumburg, Illinois (Box 2)
    (see also 2 prints in Box 4)
  - Young Israel: Southfield, Michigan (Box 2)
- Photographs: Slides
  Photographs: Slides are arranged in the same manner in which they arrived at the Bentley Library, organized by building type. An index to the slide files begins the series, itemizing by project name the structures which are represented.
  - Slide File Index (Box 2)
  - Auditoriums and Theaters (Box 2)
    (Includes State Fair Coliseum; Dallas / Ft. Worth; Poplar Creek; Pine Knob)
  - Banks and Financial Institutions (Box 2)
    (Includes Manufacturer's Bank of Southfield; Farmers & Merchants Bank; Metropolitan Federal Savings)
  - Corporate Office Buildings (Box 2)
  - General (Box 2)
  - Ford Fairlane Essex Office (Box 2)
  - Florida Telegraph Delivery National Headquarters and Trio Restaurant: Southfield, Michigan (Box 2)
  - Housing (Box 2)
    (Includes Village Green of Farmington; Holtzman & Silverman Parkside Terrace; Southfield Housing)
  - Industrial (Box 2)
    (Includes Meteor Photo Company; Foamade; Alpha Industries)
  - Lease Office Buildings (Box 2)
  - General (Box 2)
  - Liberty State Bank (Box 2)
  - Troy Place (Box 2)
  - Master Plans (Box 2)
  - General (Box 2)
  - Michigan State Fair (Box 2)
  - Medical Office Buildings (Box 2)
  - Recreation (Box 2)
  - Religious (Box 2)
  - Residential (Box 2)
  - General (Box 2)
  - Franklin Wright Camp (Box 2)
  - Restaurants (Box 2)
    (Includes Nemo's Fairlane; Kyoto Fairlane)
  - Retail (Box 2)
- Photographs: Oversized and Mounted Prints
  Most of the photographs in this series, once on the walls of Rossen's office, are mounted on boards for display.
  - Beckwith Evans General Offices: Troy, Michigan, 3 prints (Box 3)
  - Bloomfield Professional Pavilion: Bloomfield, Michigan, 4 prints (Box 3)
  - Burton Abstract and Title company Headquarters: Troy, Michigan, 4 prints (Box 3)
  - Fairlane Office and Research Building: Dearborn, Michigan, 1 prints (Box 3)
  - Farmers and Merchants State Bank: Sebewaing, Michigan, 1 prints (Box 3)
  - Farmington Professional Pavilion: Farmington, Michigan, 3 prints (Box 3)
  - Florists Trans World Delivery National Headquarters / Trio Restaurant: Southfield, Michigan, 1 prints (Box 3)
  - Foamade Industries: Pontiac Township, Michigan, 2 prints (Box 3)
  - K Mart Bee Ridge Square Office Building, 1 prints (Box 3)
  - Kimberly Scott Building: Troy, Michigan, 1 prints (Box 3)
  - Liberty State Bank: Troy, Michigan, 1 prints (Box 3)
  - Massachusetts Mutual, 1 prints (Box 3)
  - Meteor Photo Company: Troy, Michigan, 1 prints (Box 3)
  - Metropolitan Federal Savings Headquarters: Shelby Township, Michigan, 1 prints (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, unidentified, 9 prints (Box 4)
  - Pavilions, 5 prints (Box 4)
  - Residences, 4 prints (Box 4)
  - Rosin and Rosin Office, 1 prints (Box 4)
  - Salvation Army Echo Grove Camp: Leonard, Michigan, 1 prints (Box 4)
  - Terry Barr Sales Office Building: Southfield, Michigan, 1 prints (Box 4)
  - United Midwest Bancorporation Ltd.: Troy, Michigan, 2 prints (Box 4)
  - Village Green of Farmington: Farmington, Michigan, 1 prints (Box 4)
  - Woodfield Office Center: Schaumburg, Illinois, 2 prints (Box 4)